hey everyone welcome to another lesson
in the stock automation codes today we
are going to talk about an important
concept known as recovery scenarios
now no matter which automation tool you
work on you have to think about how you
can recover from unexpected failures or
errors
now in some tools this recovery feature
is already present or in some customized
automation you have to write your own
scripts to do that
so if you have been working with
selenium you have to write something
like a try catch Block in order to come
out of unexpected errors or exceptions
in Tosca there is a recovery engine
which already provides you with that
feature
so you have to provide a collection of
desktops which are called recovery
scenarios and they will kick in whenever
a test case fails
so let's see how you can configure this
recovery scenario in Tosca
so there are basically three steps in
order to configure a recovery scenario
the first step is to enable it in Tosca
and you can do it in two ways
so the first way is to go to the
settings dialog and apply it to all the
objects in the workspace
but if you want to specify it for a
particular object then you have to do it
via configuration parameters
and this will be applicable for
individual test case folders now I'll
show you how you can do this but let's
first go through all the different steps
here
the next step is to create the recovery
scenarios
and you can do it at the test case level
so either you can create it for test
case folder or the individual test cases
and the last step is to specify when
this recovery scenario should be applied
for your test cases
and that you can do using this property
which is called retry level
once you have created your recovery
scenario you can go and change this
property now it may be by default set to
test case but you can also put other
values like the step value test step and
the test case
so what does it mean it means this
recovery will kick in when a test step
value or a test step or a test case
fails now you can change it based on
your scenario or your requirement but
you have to put
um
something on this property retry level
so all of these three steps are
important and this is how you can
configure your recovery scenario for
your test cases
now let's go to Tosca and see this uh in
real time how you can apply this
coverage scenario how you can enable
them and how you can create them in your
test cases
so I have now launched my Tosca
commander and let's see how we can
enable recovery at a global level which
is for all the objects in the workspace
and that you can do by going to your
settings
and inside the settings you need to go
to t-box
Inside the Box you need to go to
recovery and here you will find
different options in order to configure
or enable your recovery scenarios
so you can enable recovery scenario at
three levels
the first is on dialogue failure
second is on exception failure and the
third is on verification failure
so the first one is related to your
failure with respect to your specific
application right so if Tosca is not
able to interact anymore with the
application due to some uh unexpected
failure then you can specify a certain
value here right so choose what those
guys should do in this case okay so let
me expand this
and here you can see all the values and
the comments okay
so there are four different values
either you can halt the execution
completely
you can execute the next test case
and you can continue with the execution
okay
or you can just do a recover now these
are all the four values if you want to
work with recoveries you have to select
recover in this particular case okay and
similarly you need to change all of
these if you want to recover from all of
these different types of failures okay
so on dialogue failure on exception
failure and on a verification failure in
all these cases Tosca should run the
recovery scenarios that's what we are
currently setting this okay
now there are three other properties
called test case retries desktop retries
and test value retracts now what are
these is these are the maximum number of
recovery attempts Tosca will do in order
to recover a particular test case a
particular test step or a particular
test step value okay
now you can choose any value or enter
any value here right you can do a two or
three or you can set different values
for all the different types okay or you
can have the same values here
so this is where you enable your
recovery at a global level for all your
objects in the workspace okay once you
do that just close this window and it
will enable the recovery for all the
objects okay
now
say for example you don't want to apply
the same level of recovery for different
uh objects on your workspace in that
case what you can do is whenever you are
creating a test case folder you can go
to test configuration so I have created
this recovery folder okay
and here under test configuration
you can add different test configuration
parameters okay so click on create test
configuration parameter and here you can
select on dialog failure okay
and you can select a value so I want to
recover
similarly again I can add another test
configuration failure and I will say on
exception failure
and I will say recover
and the last one which is on
verification failure okay and here also
I will say recover
right so this is how you can set the
recovery at a folder level right once
you do this the global settings will be
overwritten okay so whatever you specify
here will apply and not the global
settings okay and similarly you can do
it for how many times you want Tosca to
do this reattempt right so that again
you have to add a configuration
parameter so let's search for them
so this will be a test case retries okay
and I have to specify some value I'll
specify one for now
and then
you can also add the other ones like
test step
retries
and the last one which is called the
test step level three tries
or it should be
let's search for them okay set tester
value utilize
so uh here I can specify just two and
two
okay so these are all the
parameters which we have set at a test
case level okay and this will overwrite
the global entries
so our first step is now complete we
have enabled recovery uh at our test
case folder level right and now we want
to create a recovery scenario right and
how you can do that as I said earlier
you have to do it at a test case level
so go to a test case folder and here
right click and then
go here and select create recovery
scenario collection okay you can also
use the shortcuts Ctrl n and Ctrl R okay
so let's do this right now and you will
see here it will create a folder called
recovery scenarios right so this is the
parent folder again you need to right
click on this and you need to now select
create recovery scenario okay so you can
create multiple scenarios inside this
and this is our recovery scenario folder
right the difference is this is a white
plus and this is a red plus okay
now inside this we need to create a
collection of test steps right so which
can be executed when this recovery is
triggered by Tosca
but first let's understand where we will
apply this recovery and why we would
apply this right
so to do this I have made a very dumb
test okay
so what I have done is I want to click
on this submit button here right
but now what has happened is there has
been a development change right so if I
refresh this page you will see now the
submit button is disabled for around 13
or 14 seconds right so after this time
is gone then only the submit button
would be enabled right now consider for
this example this is the change and our
test is going to fail right because the
previous functionality was submit button
was always enabled and now the current
functionality is it is enabled after
some time is spanned right
so now we have to think about how we can
recover out of this failure right I can
go and directly change my test but uh if
I don't want to do that every time there
is a functionality change like this
right so I need to think of a way where
I can recover out of unexpected errors
in my executions so that my executions
are not halted because of some change or
some unexpected error right
so for this particular example
um I have created this uh three test
steps right so it will open the URL it
will click on the submit button and it
will close the page now here what I have
done is I'm also checking for whether
that button is enabled or not before I
click on that button right so ideally it
should fail here because it won't be
enabled as soon as I launch the page
right it has to wait for some time and
that's where we have to enable our
recovery scenario right
now let's first see how this execution
will fail and then we will see how we
can apply a recovery scenario to make
this pass okay
so let me close this and
let's go ahead and
run this in scratchbook now while this
is executing another important thing to
note as recovery scenario only works
when you run your test using an
execution list okay so if you run it
using a scratch book The Recovery
scenario won't kick in so it will
execute just as a simple test the
recovery scenario won't work okay
so as expected the test has failed as
you can see
and that is what we expected out of this
okay
so the submit enabled uh the
verification has failed now here I can
also apply two types of uh recoveries
right I can either do it at a test case
failure level or I can also do it at on
verification failure right so I can
basically enable it at any of these
places right
so before we add a recovery right we
need to also do the third step which is
the retry level property right so we
have to set some retry level property
value here so when you create a recovery
scenario go to the properties here you
will find the retry level and we have to
specify some level where this retry
should be kicked in so it either it
could be a test step the step value or
test case right so for this example I
will keep it as test case okay
and now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to search and add a test step here
so that uh this desktop would be
kicked in whenever the recovery scenario
is enabled okay
so here what I want to do is I want to
check or I want to wait for this
particular button to be enabled before
it goes and clicks on it okay
so that's what I want to do so I'm going
to change this action mode to wait on
and I will wait for it to be enabled
okay
so this weight on action mode uh it will
ask Tosca to wait until this particular
value is achieved for this particular
object okay
so I will rename this I will say check
submit
okay so this is my recovery scenario as
you can see and this is my test step
inside the recovery scenario now what
will happen is when this particular test
case which is the submit
uh when this fails this retrial level
will kick in and it will identify that
my test case has failed and it will ask
the recovery engine to start the
recovery scenario right so it will go
into this recovery scenario and then it
will execute this particular step which
is to wait till that particular button
is enabled and then again it will
execute the test case right so it will
again come here and it will again check
whether it is enabled and it will click
on it and then it will go to the other
steps right so this is the flow
now let's see whether it actually works
or it doesn't work right
so as I said we have to do it in
execution list right so let me track my
execution list here
and I have already created a execution
list folder so I'm going to drag this
recovery folder
into my execution list folder so that
our execution list is created here
I will say here recovery right
and this contains my recovery test case
okay
so let's go ahead and run this so that
our recovery scenario can now kick in
when there is a failure and it can
recover out of that failure so that the
test cases pass okay
so let's see this in action now
so at this point the test case is
failing but it has already kicked in the
recovery scenario where it is asking
Tosca to wait till this particular
button is enabled
and then it will again execute the test
case we'll see this all in our results
where it will be more clear what is
actually happening right so if I go back
to my execution list here
and I go to my execution
here the open URL is working fine right
and if you go into the submit if you
look carefully here the first step has
failed right the submit enabled has
failed because the submit button was not
enabled and hence it failed and then
what Tosca did is it kicked in this
recovery scenario right so where it is
waiting for that button to be enabled
right it is executing this particular
step
and after that again this step is
getting executed here right
and this is where it is coming and it is
now enabled so it is clicking on the
button and that's where this particular
test case has passed right
so it has attempted just once because I
had put in one one attempt right
if there are scenarios where you want
Tosca to attempt more than once right
you can increase the test case retries
right or the retry levels so you can do
it uh here
on the test configuration parameters so
test case three tries you can increase
this to any value right but in my case
it should be done at one retry but in
some other scenarios it might take more
retries right so you can set any values
but if the test case passes it won't go
into the other it tries okay if it fails
then it will continue retrying until
this value is reached
okay
so this is how you can use recovery
scenario to recover your test cases from
unexpected failures or unexpected
exceptions
now there is also another concept called
cleanup scenarios okay and that I would
be explaining in the next session so
keep watching our channel for more Tosca
lessons uh coming up every Friday so see
you uh next Friday with another new
Tosca lesson